WILLIAM L. CARSS:
Minnesota Historical Society
William L. Carss papers.
1918-1929.
Minnesota Historical Society
Carss, William L. (William Leighton), 1865-1931.
Correspondence, invitations, newsletters, printed materials, and related papers regarding Carss' activities as a (Farmer-Labor) U.S. representative from Minnesota's Eighth Congressional District (1919-1921, 1925-1929).
3.0 cu. ft. (3 boxes).
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Carss was born in Pella, Iowa (February 15, 1865) and was educated as a civil engineer. He moved to Proctor (Minn.) in 1893 and became a locomotive engineer. He was elected to Congress in 1918 on the Union-Labor ticket, but was defeated in 1920 and 1922. He was reelected in 1924 on the Farmer-Labor ticket for four years, being defeated again in 1928 and 1930. In 1929 Carss returned to locomotive engineering, and died in Duluth on May 31, 1931.
SCOPE AND CONTENTS
Correspondence, invitations, newsletters, printed materials, and related papers regarding Carss' activities as a (Farmer-Labor) U.S. representative from Minnesota's Eighth Congressional District (1919-1921, 1925-1929).
The collection consists largely of legislative issue files documenting Carss' efforts for his constituents, especially those in St. Louis, Lake, and Cook counties. There is information on the construction of the Duluth aerial lift bridge and harbor improvements; agitation for a Coast Guard station in Grand Marais; information on the progress of St. Lawrence Seaway proposals; the establishment of the Superior National Forest; individual immigration cases; and petitions to repeal wartime liquor prohibition laws (1919). Files of major significance include civil service appointments relating to federal employment in the district; military pensions for Civil War, Spanish-American War, and World War I veterans; and postmaster appointments and the construction of new post office buildings.
There are also political correspondence files containing letters from prominent Minnesota and national political figures, relating especially to the campaigns of 1924, 1926, and 1928, with a few items concerning the 1918 campaign. Also included in these files are correspondence, resolutions, and other papers from various labor organizations. A small collection of Washington office personal files contain correspondence between Carss and two of his Washington office staff: Helen Rawlings and Therese Pierson, with information on routine constituent matters and miscellaneous correspondence, including invitations. At the end of the collection is a small group of Carss' newsletters (1926-1928).
OTHER FINDING AIDS
A print version of this finding aid is available in the repository; filed in ALPHA notebooks under the heading: Carss, William L.
CATALOG HEADINGS
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the Minnesota Historical Society. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Topics:
Bridges -- Minnesota -- Duluth.; Bridges -- Minnesota -- Itasca County.; Civil service -- Minnesota.; Conservation of natural resources -- Minnesota.; Forest reserves -- Minnesota.; Harbors -- Minnesota -- Duluth.; Immigrants -- Minnesota.; Patronage, Political -- Minnesota.; Military pensions -- Minnesota.; Politics, Practical -- Minnesota.; Postal service -- Minnesota -- Buildings.; Postal service -- Minnesota -- Postmasters.; Prohibition -- Minnesota.; Indians of North America -- Minnesota -- Government relations.; Labor movement -- Minnesota.; Political campaigns -- Minnesota.
Organizations:
Democratic Party (U.S.).; Farmer-Labor Party (Minn.).; Great Lakes-St. Lawrence Tidewater Association.; United States. Coast Guard.
Places:
Saint Lawrence Seaway.; Superior National Forest (Minn.).; Arrowhead Region (Minn.).; Cook County (Minn.).; Duluth (Minn.).; Grand Marais (Minn.).; Lake County (Minn.).; Saint Louis County (Minn.).
Occupations:
Politicians.
ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION
Accession Information:
Accession number: 14,818
DETAILED DESCRIPTION
- Biographical Information. (1)
- Legislative Subject Files, 1919-1929:
  - American Legion.
  - Civil Service appointments., 2 folders.
  - Curling stones, Tariff on.
  - Duluth Aerial Lift Bridge.
  - Duluth-Superior harbor improvements.
  - Fish fry: Licenses request., 2 folders.
  - Grand Marais Coast Guard Station., 2 folders.
  - Great Lakes-St. Lawrence Tidewater Association., 4 folders.
  - Immigration cases; Passports and visas., 2 folders.
  - Indian affairs.
  - Irish Republic, Recognition of.
  - Itasca County bridge.
  - Parole requests.
  - Pensions, military (by individual, A-Z), 1925-1929.; 9 folders.
  - Pensions, military (larger files): (2)
    - Ashford, Charles N., 1926-1928.
    - Davison, James R., 1927-1929.
    - Hanford, Addie, 1925-1927.
  - Pensions, military: Civil War (filed by date), 1925-1928.; 2 folders.
  - Pensions, Military: Civil War (by individual, A-S), 1921-1928.; 2 folders.
  - Post offices and postmasters (by city, A-Z), 1920-1928.; 19 folders.
  - Prohibition and liquor matters, including repeal of wartime liquor laws, 1919-1929.; 2 folders.
  - Railroads: Esch-Cummins Act, 1919-1920.
  - Service academy appointments (filed by applicant's name), 1920-1928.; 3 folders.
  - Superior National Forest, 1926-1929.; 2 folders.
- Legislative Files (alphabetical, A-Y), 1925-1928.; 9 folders. (3)
- Washington Office. Personal Files:
  - Helen Rawlings correspondence, 1920, 1924.
  - Therese M. Pierson correspondence, 1925-1928.; 2 folders.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (including invitations), 1918-1929.; 3 folders.
- Correspondence and other papers regarding political activities (including labor organizations), 1918-1929.; 10 folders.
- Newsletters (1926-1928) and Speeches (1920, 1926).